<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.1.2//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.1.2/docbookx.dtd" [
  <!ENTITY legal SYSTEM "legal.xml">
  <!ENTITY appversion "1.0">
  <!ENTITY manrevision "1.0">
  <!ENTITY date "February 2006">
  <!ENTITY app "<application>My application</application>">
  <!ENTITY appname "Conduit">
]>

<article id="index" lang="en">
  <articleinfo>
    <title>&appname; Manual</title>
    <abstract role="description">
      <para>&appname; is a program that synchronizes things</para>
    </abstract>
    <copyright>
      <year>2007</year>
      <holder>John Stowers</holder>
    </copyright>
    <publisher>
      <publishername> GNOME Documentation Project </publishername>
    </publisher>

    <authorgroup>
      <author role="maintainer">
        <firstname>John</firstname>
        <surname>Stowers</surname>
      </author>
    </authorgroup>

    <revhistory>
      <revision>
        <revnumber>&appname; Manual &manrevision;</revnumber>
        <date>2006-02-04</date>
      </revision>
    </revhistory>

    <releaseinfo>This manual describes version &appversion; of &appname;</releaseinfo>
  </articleinfo>

  <section>
    <title>Introduction</title>
    <para>
      Conduit is a synchronization solution for GNOME which allows the
      user to take their emails, files, bookmarks, and any other type
      of personal information and synchronize that data with another
      computer, an online service, or even another electronic device.
    </para>

    <para>
      Conduit manages the synchronization and conversion of data into
      other formats. For example, conduit allows you to;
    </para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
	<para>
	  Synchronize your tomboy notes to a file on a remote computer
	</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
	<para>
	  Synchronize your emails to your mobile phone
	</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
	<para>
	  Synchronize your bookmarks to delicious, gmail, or even your
	  own webserver
	</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
	<para>
	  and many more... 
	</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para>
      Any combination you can imagine, Conduit will take care of the
      conversion and synchronization.
    </para>

    <section>
      <title>What Can Conduit Do</title>

      <para>
	From an end user perspective Conduit has reached the level of
	being useful. Conduit can currently perform the following sync
	partnerships;
      </para>
      
      <itemizedlist>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    Two way file/folder sync on gnomevfs volumes and to/from Box.net
	  </para>
	</listitem>

	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    Two way Tomboy note sync via gnomevfs volumes
	  </para>
	</listitem>

	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    Two way Tomboy note sync via ipod notes
	  </para>
	</listitem>

	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    One way sync of files/folders of photos to Flickr, Smugmug and Picasa	    
	  </para>
	</listitem>

	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    One way sync of FSpot tagged photos to Flickr, Smugmug and Picasa	    
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	

	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    Sync and export of Evolution memos and tasks to ipod and to a folder.  
	  </para>
	</listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      
      <para>
	In the one way sync/export case Conduit is smart in the sense that if
	a piece of data has not been modified then it will not be
	synchronized/exported again, it will replace the existing data. In
	addition if data is subsequently removed from a source then its
	corresponding data will also be deleted.
      </para>
      
      <para>
	Conduit has a full featured DBus interface to allow other application
	authors to use Conduit to perform the synchronization and export tasks
	of their applications.
      </para>
    </section>
    
    <section>
      <title>Whats Planned For Future</title>
      
      <itemizedlist>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    SyncML support
	  </para>
	</listitem>

	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    Google gdata support (Notes, docs, base)
	  </para>
	</listitem>

	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    Direct PC-PC sync over local LAN using Avahi
	  </para>
	</listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>
  </section>
  
  <section>
    <title>How to use the GUI</title>
    <para>
      Grab a dataprovider from the left panel and drag it on to the
      canvas on the right.  Right click on the icon in the canvas to
      bring up a context menu.  Double click to configure the item.
    </para>
  </section>
</article>

